welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
[Music]
welcome to the stoa i'm peter limberg
the steward of the stoa and the stow is
a place for us to go here and dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of this
moment and today we got donald robinson
big d
it's in the house um so
we're gonna do a little uh something
different here we're gonna do a little
ice breaking exercise i'm gonna throw
everyone in breakout rooms
for two minutes one minute each uh just
introduce yourself
uh maybe how you got uh you heard of the
stole or this event
and what is your expectations uh for
today
and just you know get to know each other
uh and then we'll come back here and
we'll start uh
the exercise so i will do that
now
begin i think people are coming back all
right everyone welcome back
hope you had a fun little icebreaker so
today
as i mentioned we have donald robinson
visiting
the stoa and donald is really the
central node for the modern stoicism
movement without him
um you know stoicism probably wouldn't
have the buzz it has today
uh he's the organizer probably central
organizer for the annual stoic
conference
stoicon um yeah he's just a general
stoic super user
author of a few books like how to think
like a roman emperor which has just
recently came out
sources in the art of happiness and the
philosophy of cognitive behavioral
therapy and how it relates to stoicism
so today uh if you were at the the
stoicon last oakcon in toronto uh donna
robinson was there and he did
a stoic exercise called view from above
and we're gonna do that today
uh it's one of the the stoic uh
psychotechnologies or life practices
uh so donald's going to talk briefly
about it we're going to do it
collectively as a group
uh it's a meditative exercise and then
we're going to have
a q a to for the rest of the hour
so that being said i'm going to hand it
over to donald
thanks very much peter so i'm just going
to say a little preamble and then
we thought we just launched straight
into doing the exercise today
and uh you know the main thing i'd like
to say about the view from above
is it's one of the most iconic stoic
exercises in a sense everyone always
talks about it and recognizes it um we
don't know what the stoics
call it pierre haddos a modern scholar
gave it the the name the view from above
it's found in other philosophical
traditions but i just want to say a
little bit about why i think it's
important
when i first began studying stoicism
which is nearly 25 years ago
now the the first book i wrote which
i've got here actually
i tried to do like a the philosophy of
cbt i tried to do a
survey of the relationship between
ancient stoic techniques or psycho
technology
and modern psychotherapy and
i found a lot of parallels but there was
one technique that really jumped out
that seemed quite prominent
and uh quite important that doesn't
really resemble one of the main
techniques found in modern psychotherapy
you'll find things that are a bit like
it
but it's not a central focus it's not
common technique
in modern psychotherapy and that's a
view from above and i thought
it makes sense like it looks like a
technique that you could script and do
an audio recording of
there's different ways you could do it
so i used to do it with groups of
psychotherapists i ran a training school
for psychotherapists in uk i used to
speak at
psychotherapy conferences and uh
i wrote about it in psychotherapy
journals and we've got i had roomfuls of
hundreds of psychtherapists doing and
stuff so i got to get their feedback on
it
and they really enjoyed doing it and
so did an audio recording and i put it
online and
a chap called patrick fisher who was a
phd student at the university of exeter
found the recording and played it to a
group of graduate students there
and he had been doing this thing called
live like galen
for a week marcus releases court
physician following his
health and lifestyle advice and so
patrick thought we could take
this and we could do live like marcus
aurelius for a week
and he went to his supervisor who was
christopher gill
who's now professor emeritus of ancient
thought at extra university
and so they started experimenting with
the recording and then they got me to go
down to extra with a bunch of other
people and that was the beginning of the
modern stories as an organization
in 2011 or 2012 and it was the beginning
of what we now call stoic week
so the whole thing in a sense began
because i looked at all about 18
different psychological techniques i
found
and this one jumped out because i
thought we don't really do this in psych
therapy but we could
and then we started doing it and people
really liked it and they thought yeah we
should be doing this
and then that became the central
technique of
the online course that we ran every year
so
a little bit of the history and how it
seemed to kind of appeal to people
and so with that in mind i thought we
could just launch
straight into doing the exercise if
everybody
is ready to begin so
let's begin you can do this process
either
seated or lying down if you want
take a moment to settle into your
posture and make yourself comfortable
and close your eyes and relax
be aware of your breathing and notice
the
rhythm and pattern of the breath
and do nothing for a while just be
content to
contemplate your breathing more deeply
now begin by paying attention to the
whole of your body
as one from the top of your head all the
way down into your
fingers and down into your toes
be aware of your whole body every nerve
muscle and fiber don't try to change
anything
and don't try to stop anything from
changing
some things change just by being
observed
now just imagine that you're taking a
step back and
looking at yourself and it really
doesn't matter how vividly you can
picture yourself it's just the
intention just the idea that counts
imagine
you can see your body posture your
facial expression
the color and style of your clothing
now keep looking at the image of
yourself resting there
and imagine leaving the ground as you
gaze down
at your body you begin
floating serenely upwards slowly
continuously rising upwards
all the while your gaze keeps returning
to your body
which remains there below you as you
rise above it
keep looking down towards your body as
you float higher
and higher you can imagine the roof
and ceiling disappearing allowing you to
float freely upward
gazing down you see yourself relaxing
comfortably below in the building
looking content and contemplative
you can see all the rooms and any other
people around
as you continue to float gently higher
and higher your
perspective widens more and more
until you see the whole surrounding area
you see all the buildings nearby from
above
you see the people in the buildings and
in the streets and roads
you observe people far below working
walking along the
sidewalk pavement people cycling or
driving their cars
and those traveling on buses and trains
you begin to contemplate the whole
network of human lives and
how people everywhere are interacting
with each other
influencing each other encountering each
other in
different ways
floating higher people become as small
as ants below
rising up into the clouds you see the
whole of the surrounding region beneath
you
you see both towns and countryside and
maybe the coastline comes into view
as your perspective becomes more and
more expansive
you float gently up above the clouds
above the weather
and through the upper atmosphere of the
planet earth
so high that you eventually rise beyond
the sphere of the planet itself and
into outer space you look toward planet
earth and see it suspended in space
before you
silently turning resplendent and not all
its majesty and beauty
you contemplate all the countless living
beings upon the earth
the population of the planets over six
billion people
you realize that your life is just one
among many one
person among the total population of the
earth
you think of how rich and diverse
human life on earth is
and yet as you gaze upon the earth
you're also aware of its position within
the rest of the universe a
tiny speck of stardust adrift in the
immeasurable
vastness of cosmic space this world of
ours is merely a tiny grain of sand by
comparison with the
endless tracts of space a tiny rock in
space
revolving around our sun the sun itself
is just one of countless billions of
stars which
punctuate the velvet blackness of our
galaxy
you think about the present moment on
earth and see it within the broader
context of your life as a whole you
think of your
life span as a whole and its totality
you think of your own life as one moment
in the enormous
lifespan of mankind hundreds of
generations
have lived and died before you and many
more will live and die in the future
long after you yourself are gone
civilizations too have a lifespan and
you think of the many great cities which
have
arisen and been destroyed throughout the
ages
and your own civilization as one in a
series
perhaps in the future to be followed by
new cities
peoples languages cultures and
ways of life you think of the lifespan
of humanity
as a whole just one of countless
billions of species living upon the
planet
mankind arose as a race roughly 200
thousand years ago
animal life itself first appeared on
earth over four billion years ago
contemplate time as follows realize that
if the history of life and earth filled
an encyclopedia
a thousand pages long the life of the
entire human race
can be represented by a single sentence
in that book just one sentence
you contemplate all things past present
and future
you see your life within the bigger
picture the total
context of cosmic space and time
you see yourself as an integral part of
something much bigger something truly
vast
just like the cells of your own body
work together to form a
greater unity a living being so your
body as a whole
is like a single cell in the organism of
the universe
along with every atom in the universe
you contribute your role to the
unfolding of its
vast design as your consciousness
expands and your mind stretches out to
reach the vastness of eternity
things change greatly in perspective
and shifts occur in their relative
importance
trivial things seem trivial to you
and different things seem indifferent
the significance of your own
attitude towards life becomes more
apparent
you realize that life is what you make
of it you learn to put things in
perspective and focus on your true
values and priorities in life
one stage to time you develop the
serenity to accept
things you cannot change the courage to
change the things you can
and the wisdom to know the difference
you follow nature your own true nature
is a rational
truth-seeking human being and the one
great nature of the universe as a whole
now in a moment you're beginning to sink
back down to earth
towards your place in the here and now
part of you can remain aware of the view
from above and
always return to and remember that sense
of serenity
and perspective now you begin your
descent back down to earth to face the
future with renewed
strength and equanimity you sink back
down through the sky down down
down towards the local area
down down into the building
down you sink back gently into your body
all the way now as your feet slowly come
to rest upon the floor
once again now think about the room
around you
think about action movement think about
looking around and getting your
orientation
raising your head a little begin to
breathe a little bit more deeply
a little bit more energetically let your
body feel more alive
and ready for action as you breathe
energy and vitality
into your body breathe a little deeper
and deeper again until you're ready to
take a
deep breath open your eyes and emerge
from the meditation
taking your mindfulness and
self-awareness forward
into life beginning now taking a deep
breath
and opening your eyes and when you're
ready just entering the here and now
with deep calm and serenity
so there we are the view from above
exercise a slightly
abbreviated version of the
the recording actually that we use for
stoic week
um so if it's okay i don't know how we
are for time people but maybe i'll
i follow do you want me to talk a little
bit more about
the significance of the exercise and
then we'll do some q a in a little bit
yeah i think that would be good maybe
talk a little bit more and then if you
have any questions start putting in the
chat box now and then i'll call on you
when
we have the q a portion cool okay so
i'll just mention a couple of little
bits of travia i think might be useful
because i assume most of you are
quite familiar with stoicism so i'll
just tell you some bits and pieces about
the view from above
so first of all when i was comparing it
to cbt techniques i couldn't find a
technique that was similar to that
but all of the stoic techniques can be
understood
in terms of the broad cognitive strategy
in a kind of abstract sense so there are
techniques that involve
expanding our awareness of time
or space but they don't take exactly the
same form as that
so one of them actually in cbt would be
um when somebody's worrying about
something one of my favorite techniques
i think one of the most powerful
techniques
there are visual techniques physical
uh emotional techniques verbal cognitive
techniques that we have in therapy we
can
lump together what peter calls the
psycho technology under these different
categories
so this is a verbal technique um so
somebody's worrying about a field
catastrophe
we can just say what do you think's
probably going to happen next
so i think my girlfriend might dump me
what do you think's probably going to
happen next
well i guess i'll feel really sad about
it and then what do you think's probably
going to happen next but i guess
i'll sell home and cry in my beer and
then what's probably going to happen
next well i guess eventually i'll have
to start going out and socializing again
most probably going to happen next
well i guess eventually i'll meet
someone else and then what's probably
going to happen next
i guess i'll have another relationship
and so
we can encourage people just by asking
that question to expand their temporal
perspective a bit
and that is a very powerful form of
decatastrophizing
there are techniques i know from
teaching therapists that look cool on
paper
and then there are techniques that are
hard to explain that work very robustly
in practice
and that's a technique that's so simple
that people might overlook it but it
works very robustly
in a consulting room setting so almost
always if you just ask that question
repeatedly it has a very
simple very powerful effect
another technique is future cell therapy
or time projection or whatever we
have lots of different names in therapy
field for the same techniques
so we might get someone to put
themselves in the future imagine
themselves 10 years from now looking
back
on their current situation imagine what
advice their future self would give them
and that's another way of kind of
broadening your temporal perspective
um another thing i'd mention about the
view from above there's
one of the things that really appeals to
me about it that
there are techniques in stoicism that
cognitive therapists and researchers
would immediately look at
and go that looks like it should work
like so that doesn't mean that it is
going to work um but in this
any field of research does this
frustration you see this now actually
with the reception the pandemic
a good example actually would be the
wearing of masks so if you read the
scientific
literature most researchers are like
wearing masks should help but we don't
have a direct
uh test of that at the moment we're
still kind of pending
solid data that directly verifies that
but from everything that we
know about the like the the science of
this already it's
so highly suggestive so the view from
above
is something that any cognitive
therapist or psychologist would look at
and think
that looks like it should do something
like
and even you know prior to having
carried out a controlled
trial on it and there are a number of
reasons for that but one of them is
for a start it's a very simple technique
and it can be scripted
so you would be able to look at and go
reliably we could get people to broaden
their perspective
and and so it looks like we should be
consistently able to do
a fairly dramatic cognitive change with
this technique
and it kind of looks like it should
change people's emotions as well
and maybe change their cognitive
processing a bit so
you know anyone looking at would think
that's worth trying
um but also there's a body of
a whole bunch of converging research
that shows
that when people are anxious or also
when they're angry
um and maybe else even when they're
depressed they tend to
narrow down the scope of their attention
so normally we can walk in true
government as i like to say
so we can pay attention to multiple
things at once we could be driving the
car
and having a conversation with someone
in the back seat and also thinking about
what we're going to make for dinner
so we can do pay attention to multiple
things but under stress we can't
like our attention becomes narrowed in
scope
and it's kind of like we put the stress
cues or the anxiety cues the things that
are freaking us out
under a magnifying glass and they also
captivate our attention more
and so recently over the past and by
recent i mean over the last
15 years roughly there's been increasing
interest
in attentional training techniques and
psychotherapy
because um the stuff that goes on in
your head
that's involuntary and then there's
other stuff that's under voluntary
strategic control as we call that and
the way that you allocate your attention
is kind of in between there are aspects
of it that are under voluntary control
so we know you could train
people to broaden the scope of their
attention
to externalize their attention rather
than focusing it inwardly and stuff like
that
and there's good emerging evidence that
shows that that has a profound effect in
the treatment of anxiety
and depression so it's a cutting-edge
topic
in psychotherapy research but the stoics
were way ahead of the game
two and a half thousand years ago by
thinking we should be broadening our
attention
in perspective that's antagonistic it's
the opposite
to what happens when people are stressed
out anxious or angry
and there are a number of ways of seeing
this so if you're frightened
and you narrow your attention onto the
scariest thing in the room
and you put it under a magnifying glass
that's going to amplify your anxiety
and it's also going to be kind of
limiting because you're not taking in
other sources of information
that might benefit you we sometimes call
those safety cues so might be reassuring
things
so there might be some scary monster in
the room but you've got a whole bunch of
bodyguards around you for example
so if you're only focusing on the scary
monster not taking in the presence of
the bodyguards you have a very
negatively biased
perception so you get a more
balanced nuanced and complex emotional
response
when you're able to broaden your
perspective and take in a variety of
different stimuli
at once for healthy to do that and so
the stoics are generally doing that
so a couple of that's some of the kind
of cognitive science if you like
a couple of other bits of trivia this
technique is found in
a lot of ancient literature not just the
stoics
we don't really know how or where it
originated it seems almost intuitive
some people have described it as almost
a such shamanistic technique weirdly
um our earliest sources for information
on socrates
are satires that ridicule him so
aristophanes wrote a play called the
clouds it was performed in the theater
of dionysus in athens
and it mocks socrates by portraying
socrates
in a theatrical crane
suspended above his school
called the thinkery while his students
are bending over
looking at maps on the ground so he
seems to be
almost ridiculing or satirizing the
something like the view from above like
socrates is suspended
among the clouds looking down his
students who are also looking down
uh maps of the the known world and
contemplating a map
or a diagram would be another way of
practicing
the view from above which i guess leads
me on to another observation
which is in the ancient world you could
compare this
and people have done to kind of two
themes and one
is uh if you imagine the view of the
gods looking down from mount olympus
you've all seen things like clash of the
titans where zeus is looking down and
humans are like little chess pieces and
so this kind of image of the gods
looking down from olympus
naturally evokes the idea of the view
from above and so in a sense that
very much the stoics thought of it as a
way of entering or emulating the mind of
zeus
so becoming more godlike and this is
kind of the goal of philosophy
but to enter into this perspective is
also to enter into the
the mind of the the sophos the wise man
or woman
likes a practicing review from above is
kind of a perspective shifting exercise
that allows us to get more into a
god-like
or sage-like perspective but it's also
there's another way of looking at it
which is less mythological
and more cosmological and so when
ancient philosophers discuss
the nature of the universe and time as a
whole
whenever they discuss it or draw
diagrams of it
you can imagine that as a contemplative
exercise so when they're discussing
what they they think the planets are
like what the universe looks like
this is like a meditation to them and
again when they're ridiculing socrates
as resembling natural philosophers and
looking down at these maps and stuff
this is more in the cosmological
tradition he's
he's like a proto-scientist almost but
he's trying to encompass the whole
universe and his
his mind in this way um
and there's one other thing now i'll
make a
a geographical observation about this
when marcus
describes the view from above he says
imagine law courts and
political assemblies and people trading
and arguing and milling around
and he says in the agorai in the agoras
the marketplaces or city centers and
it just so happens that in athens where
socrates lived
like in many ancient uh towns it grew up
around a hill called the acropolis
which literally means like acro like
acrobat
and paulus like uh metropolis it means
the high up part of the city
so the view from above is the view from
the athenian acropolis
where the parthenon is located the
temple of athena the goddess of wisdom
socrates would have been familiar with
this perspective he only had to walk up
the hill
or any of the other hills surrounding
athens and looked down and he would have
literally
seen the agora where he was subsequently
to be put on trial and executed one day
so if you think of it when marcus
aurelius is describing this he very much
sounds like
he could be describing the view from the
athenian
acropolis literally you could walk up
there and look down in the
and agora guess one other thing i might
mention about to take it back to cbt and
cognitive therapy some of you who have
read books on cbt will be
aware of this idea which we don't use as
much anymore
but in second wave cbt there was a lot
of talk about thinking errors or
cognitive distortions
and they are kind of useful in some ways
so one of them is called selective
abstraction and bec defined that as the
process of focusing on a detail
taken out of context and ignoring the
most salient features of the situation
such as safety cues and conceptualizing
the whole experience on the basis of
this element
which is a convoluted way of saying
selective thinking selective awareness
like it's also called having a mental
filter i would also call a lie of a
mission
to yourself or a half truth so one of
the cognitive
distortions is taking things out of
context
and putting things back in a broader
context would be like what the stoics
are doing
with the view from above and this
thinking error or cognitive distortion
or bias
is also linked to other errors that we
call magnification
or catastrophizing because when we put
things in a bigger context we're more
likely to de-catastrophizing them
and and also to over-generalization
because when we think of things in terms
of a much bigger context
we're more likely to see them as part of
a more complex
and varied and diverse richer experience
and less likely to
over generalize on the basis of a single
abstraction
so we can think of this in in terms of
rectifying thinking errors as well
and then there's one more thing i'd say
before i guess we maybe we have some
discussion
pierre hadou is one of my favorite
scholars in
in the stoicism field one of my favorite
academics said that the view from above
in a sense
is one of the most important stoic
contemplative exercises
because especially if you practice it
about you realize it kind of brings
together
many of the other stoic themes so
sometimes people can get lost in the
uh lost in the weeds of stoicism like i
said there are 18 distinct
psychological techniques that i
identified in my the first book that i
wrote about
it but many of those techniques are
evoked by the viewer from above
so for example some of the concepts and
techniques are
when we think of the view from above
it's closely linked
to stoic theology because stoics were
pantheists and they believed the
universe as a whole was divine
so if you believe the universe as a
whole is sacred then
you have a kind of religious obligation
piety would consist
in trying to contemplate the totality of
things
to put the universe back together and
that's doing the view from above it's
contemplating god
for the stoics and also the stoic idea
of determinism like seeing things as
having
physical material causes leading up to
them in particular
is a major part of being surprised by
things
so when we do the view from above we
think of things within their historical
context that's linked
to stoic determinism it's also linked to
the stoic
contemplation of impermanence or the
transience of things
because when you broaden your temporal
perspective you have to take in
the moment when you have something but
you also imagine
the potential future when it's going to
be gone or the time before it even
existed
and then that would apply to yourself as
well so it's also linked to the
military thanatos or the contemplation
of our own mortality if you do the view
from above
and think about your life within the
history of the universe you'll
necessarily think of it as a small blip
and
you'll think about the time before you
were born and after you'll be gone
another theme for the stoics is the
reversal of fortune the wheel of fortune
that someone might lose a girlfriend and
that seems like a
catastrophe but then later they might
find another one a better relationship
they might lose a job
and find a better job they might win the
lottery but then might go on to lose all
their friends or squander the money on
drugs or something
so this idea that fortune goes up and
down and there are many reversals of
fortune
it's something that we necessarily evoke
when we start to picture the bigger
perspective
um and again i think it all comes back
to the stoic idea of
trying to stretch your mind to tap in to
this inner resource
that allows us somehow the stoic stop by
some miracle
we had nature has given us this capacity
to imagine what the sage might think
even though we're not sages
we can kind of imagine what a sage might
think
by stretching our minds and using our
imagination
and this exercise of contemplating the
sage is also facilitated by the view
from above because the sage
would necessarily be somebody who's more
attuned
to the bigger perspective and that is
uh my little run through of some trivia
i guess
that i thought might quit your appetite
for a discussion what do you think of
that peter
yeah yeah we had some um questions
already in the chat box and i have a few
one
uh question for you right now uh so if
anyone has any questions throw in the
chat box you want me to read on your
behalf let me know this will go on
youtube
um so we we were talking about this
before
uh sort of like you know john vicki
calls it the ecology of practices
and a very curious like a stoic ecology
of practice or stoic proper ecology of
practice
um and stoic week is kind of like that
and also sort of like a psychology of
practices that can kind of
be figured out collectively so just like
because the one thing that's kind of
cool about
stoicism is that the lineage has been
cut so we don't really know how
pastel it's practiced so we can be
entrepreneurial in the sense um
any thoughts on how that's emerging
right now in the modern stoic movement
and how it could emerge
i think there's so much opportunity i
think hadou was like a real
god centers and the strange thing about
pr hadou was he did a very thorough
review of the ancient literature
and listed what he called spiritual
exercises and what
what struck me was that he never made
any connection with modern psychology
so he kind of handed this thesis to me
on a play
you know he's hadou says here's all the
different exercises in the stoics and
classical philosophy
and they left it to other people like i
was able to come along and go oh this is
how they compare to things that we do
in modern psychotherapy but i've only
scratched the surface
and you know there's a huge opportunity
for other people now who are
interested in modern personal
development literature psychological
research
modern philosophy psychotherapy to see
other connections and there's a huge
opportunity to do research on stoic
techniques and refine them
as a consequence of doing research to
compare it to
ideas and resilience building and
positive psychology and other
psychological psychological traditions
not just cbte
so we we now have all these online
communities where people can share their
experiences
and give feedback and also well you know
we can actually
carry out all sorts of apply all sorts
of different research methods
to the stoic techniques and modern
stoicism is kind of doing that
we're finding some things out so we're
finding out which techniques people seem
to find easiest
which are more beneficial for them you
know which ones maybe
they use more consistently over the
longer term these are all things we can
test as well as the actual
psychological effect of some of these
techniques
and refinements in practice i think
emerge from you know
playing around with things in all those
different ways
cool cool um okay so uh
pranab if you want to unmute yourself
and read your question
sure um thanks for yeah thanks for
exercise thanks for your work it's been
really great
um from your research and experience
what are some of the limits of
cbt and other cognitive behavioral
techniques where other techniques could
be more effective and are there certain
conditions or mindsets of people of like
where you kind of draw that line um
or just want to hear you think about
that oh boy that would take a whole day
to like a lot of good questions i i
could probably talk all day about that
so i have to think of the best way to
to give you the kenneth tldr abbreviated
version
um first thing i'd say is that cbt is
already
um from a previous generation
right so the the founders of cbt did the
pioneering work in the
19 even in the 1950s uh 1960s 1970s
it didn't really become mainstream
properly until the 1980s
um was ages ago now like that was
decades ago
and and actually subsequent generations
are getting
the the generation that followed them
are getting a bit old now
so we've already moved beyond cbt to
some extent so we
we talk about three waves in
psychotherapy in
an evidence-based tradition so there's
behavior therapy which
kind of it's hard to date in a way but
it sort of originated in the 50s
and then the second wave of back and
ellis and cognitive therapy
it's haiti if you like was in the 60s
70s 80s
and then from the 1990s onwards we have
what we call the third wave
of uh cbt or acceptance and commitment
therapy
and other mindfulness and acceptance
based approaches
so i i don't know there are two ways i
could answer you one is to say well what
if we look even beyond that stuff
like but i think we're kind of still in
the middle of the third wave so maybe i
would say the
things we know are
one of the limitations of cbt is that
it's
kind of overly analytical and verbal and
people that are prone to
overthinking um like some
clients with obsessive traits like ocd
health anxiety generalized anxiety
disorder
um even some depressed clients are prone
to kind of
ruminate overthink over analyze things
and traditional or second wave cognitive
therapy
sometimes backfired with those clients
so i'll give you a concrete example of
that
if you have a client with generalized
anxiety disorder pathological worrying
you could call it
and you give them a thought record like
you may have seen in cbt write down your
thoughts
man they'll come back at the next
session and they might have a pile of
papers like that deep
right and then the therapist should have
alarm bells ringing thinking
this looks more like a symptom than a
therapy
like it looks like it looks like they've
turned the therapy into
uh an extension of their symptom so
they're writing way too much stuff and
it's probably not
beneficial beyond that point so the the
third wave approaches
have focused on actually
having kind of meta approach getting
people to step back from the thinking
and notice when the thinking's going on
too long
notice the consequences of the style of
thinking
and basically to learn to manage
rumination or perseverative
thinking styles that's a ah an important
part
another thing was the second wave cbt
acknowledged cognitive distancing
but beck thought the if you're going to
dispute people if you're going to get
people's faulty
thinking and then getting to weigh up
the evidence for it which is what we did
used to do in second wave cbt still do
to
in some ways um is a preamble a
precursor to that
a prerequisite to it it has to be up for
debate
so if somebody thinks this is a
catastrophe that i've lost my job
um and you're going to get them to weigh
up the evidence for that and so on
that they have to be able to think well
maybe there are other ways of looking at
it
but if they think no it just is a
catastrophe it's a fact
then they don't have enough separation
to even begin
questioning it right so beck thought
well before we even get started we're
going to have to get them to realize
that they're catastrophizing it that
this is just one
arbitrary way of looking at it and there
might be better or
alternative ways of seeing it and then
so he'd get clients to do that and then
he'd say okay let's weigh up the
evidence for
whether or not it's a catastrophe and so
right but
what people realized was the the the
cognitive distancing approach was far
more powerful than they realized and
maybe that could almost be a whole
therapy in its own right and they
realize that when you get people to just
do focus more on the distancing um
it starts to kind of resemble stuff that
goes on in mindfulness meditation
practice
because if you're doing meditation you
don't start shredding all your thoughts
and weighing up the evidence for them
that would be like overthinking
if you notice a negative thought you
just kind of take a step back and look
at it and go oh hi
and respond as if it's just a cloud
passing across the sky
you don't get in a debate with it um
and so the idea of just doing cognitive
distancing would be kind of like
meditating
and so for 10 15 20 years or so people
have been doing research on that and
they've substantiated that hypothesis
it's it's clear now um the
cognitive distancing might be more
important than cognitive disputation
and that encouraging people to do too
much disputation might have been
kind of leading them down the wrong path
in some cases
so that that's one answer but then i
would say that in some ways the stoics
already knew that
i think um you don't actually see the
stoics
putting the same kind of emphasis on
evaluating evidence that vectored
um you know what what they go on about
is just realizing
that our value judgments are
uh fundamentally misplaced
and they're the source of our suffering
and that that's cognitive distancing
so i think it was kind of a mistake when
people thought
the um stoicism resembled back
because stoicism kind of went beyond
beck and in some ways it's more like the
third wave approaches that have emerged
subsequently
does it i hope that answers your
question that was great thank you
uh to piggyback on that david you had uh
some thoughts to share on cbt
and some buddhist traditions i believe
sure donald i welcome your uh
reflections
on um so i work at a cbt
clinic i'm also a meditation teacher
and in the 10 plus years i've been there
people have gone from
whispering that they're looking forward
to my talk on mindfulness
so actually doing some research on
this um i'm also currently looking
at hedo and socrates
and to keep it brief ways
in which early philosophy was
a transformative and essentially
spiritual
enterprise cbt
is still kind of inheriting the
positivist
science envy get things that are
measurable
get things we can put onto a a survey
in general what's your take
on the relationship between cbt-informed
psychotherapy and what's traditionally
been
more categorized as spiritual even
religious
practices in humanity well that's
another
phd thesis type question that i could
talk about for like a week or something
so i'll try and think
what would be the best thing to sell
select out and focus on
i mean i'll tell you i'll answer it my
way really and then and then maybe i'll
have a think about
what you might be driving at i when i
wrote this book funnily enough
um one of the things i said in it
is the look it seems to me
it is a fair way actually before i even
discovered stoicism
i felt as a cbt practitioner the
um the fundamental thing that determined
our thinking errors and so on were our
moral values and i
thought for example someone's really
materialistic and the the
everything for them turns on um
accumulating wealth
or if somebody's really kind of
preoccupied with what other people think
of them
that's kind of their philosophy of life
you know those are their underlying
values and they inherit them
to some extent from the prevailing
culture and uh you know we can
get people to reevaluate those in
therapy but there's kind of a problem
with doing that in a way
which is this thing of therapist
neutrality
so you you can kind of go so far
in a conventional consulting room
setting but arguably the therapist
shouldn't try and um indoctrinate the
client into a particular set of moral
values
you know certainly if you phrase it like
that people go oh no no like the
therapist shouldn't be
indoctrinating the client now what you
might assume if you're a socratic
would be that if you get people to
reflect and question
their values they're often going to end
up in a similar place
but nevertheless i felt that you know
people
used to say to me do you teach stoicism
to therapy clients
and i i used to think well i can't yes
and no
usually in practice what happens is that
they know that i write about stoicism
and so they jostle up and ask me about
it but i can't start teaching stoicism
to people in the way that i do cbt with
them
because stoicism is uh
a moral philosophy um like if they're a
muslim
or a christian or a marxist or whatever
they are the values implicit and sources
might conflict in some ways with their
existing moral values and worldview so i
can kind of
introduce it and talk to them about it
but i can't just indoctrinate them into
stoicism
they might not agree with it as a
philosophy
so the the there's an interesting
question there though about whether
certain world views and sets of moral
values
nevertheless might turn out to be
healthier than others
and i feel that the stoic worldview is
healthy but i do wonder
whether although it can kind of come
into the traditional consulting room
therapy in some ways
um whether there's a slightly different
role
for stoicism it's something that people
elect to embrace a deeper
more moral and philosophical level
almost like converting to religion
like converting to christianity or
something like that and i do wonder
whether
there's a little bit of that with
introducing buddhist themes to clients
and in therapy
i i thought early on that you know that
there are going to be some clients who
say they don't like the whole idea of
anything associated with buddhism
because
they're maybe um very orthodox christian
or or they follow some other religion or
the they're
other a kind of odd atheist in a a way
that
you know maybe they see buddhism as
conflicting with that and i think that's
kind of emerged a little bit more over
time that there are some clients that
that don't like the idea of of
doing something associated with a a
quasi religion
in in the consulting room setting um
so i think stoicism's great strength is
its greatest weakness in a way
it's too ideological it's too kind of
moral it's too spiritual
in some ways to be delivered in a normal
cbt framework
but in other respects that's precisely
what makes it so profound and so
powerful
i wonder what you think of that i don't
know if i answered gets to the gist of
your question or not but
that's kind of where i came at it from
well it very much
touches on it and i'm rather
overeducated in both
arenas psychotherapy phd and a couple of
master's degrees in religious studies
and advisors in each department who are
pretty sure i belonged in the other
department
yeah the emphasis i'm hearing as sort of
the healthy heart
of psychotherapy cbt stoicism is on the
actual
experiential procedures on the actual
practices and of course hedo
emphasizes that as you you've pointed
out so
finding you also looking to socratic
methods getting
people to connect with what they already
know
and kind of setting aside some of the
categories the boxes this is such and
such a religion or this is this
such philosophical tradition we've
always got that sort of inheritance
but again a healthy heart seems to me
if you want to help somebody change love
them the way they are and help put them
in touch with what they
already know with that kind of toolkit
of practices
okay in that case and in response to
what you said i think i would need to
introduce a distinction
um so the
there are a bunch of techniques and
stoicism and concepts that we can
apply now many of those are actually
shared with epicureanism and platonism
and aristotelianism and other
uh hellenistic uh and classical
philosophical traditions
so they're not entirely uh
exclusive to stoicism so what academics
in this field would say
is that what makes stoicism stoicism
like the beating heart of stoicism the
defining characteristic of stoicism
is its moral philosophy that says that
arity is the only true good
right and that it's at that point i
think that it becomes more problematic
so in terms of like the 18 techniques or
so yeah sure we can take most of those
techniques
and we could do them in a buddhist
framework we could do them in an atheist
framework we could do them
in a christian framework as hadou talks
about
but people would say well is that
stoicism anymore are those just kind of
accidental features of stoicism
that you could also have taken from
epicureanism as well
is the thing that the marcus aurelius
thinks defines stoicism and the things
that the other stoics think really
define their
philosophy and make it what is would be
this idea that are they rita
is the only true good and that would
arguably
clash with it might not be completely
irreconcilable with
but it's certainly on the face of it
there's a there's a real question mark
over whether you can reconcile that
with christian ethics or buddhist ethics
or marxist ethics
like because it's essentially a
particular moral doctrine
and what intrigued me was that i believe
that following that moral doctrine has
mental health benefits and contributes
to
emotional resilience but it may be that
that some people don't agree with it
and and they hold different moral values
that clash with that
and what in which case if they took the
techniques from stoicism they might
end up turning it uh into something
that's more like epicureanism or
more like greek skepticism or something
like that um
so but definitely in terms of just
taking the techniques out of stories as
i'm sure we can
absolutely assimilate those into
psychotherapy but
the question people will then raise is
is this still stoicism that we're
talking about
or is it just a kind of eclectic
derivative of hellenistic philosophy
well there's nothing wrong with doing
that
okay um we are about uh at the hour mark
so we're going to stop the questions
there there's a few other questions we
didn't uh
um get to so uh um
donald is anything uh you'd like to
leave people off where they can find you
what you're doing right now with uh
the modern sources of movement
yeah a couple of things that might uh be
worth mentioning
so we i don't know if you guys have
heard but there's this thing
happening at the moment called the
pandemic and it's been in the news a lot
and stuff
so we normally we have a conference
every year
and we're not going to be able to do
that this year we're going to have it in
toronto
so like everyone else um and as we're
doing right now we're probably going to
end up having it on zoom or something
similar around about october
so just to give you the heads up about
that we haven't really announced all the
details yet but we do have a bunch of
speakers
ready and so we're going to have an
online virtual conference
for stoicism round about october so go
see the modern stoicism.com
website so modern store system in case
anyone doesn't know is a non-profit
organization
uh headed by christopher gill and it's
run by a multi-disciplinary
team of volunteers myself included
and so it runs the conference and stoic
week and all these other things every
year
so go to modernstoresystem.com for
information and support the organization
we've also we've got a new podcast out
as well you can find information about
that there
um in terms of what i'm doing like i'm
doing something no one's going to hear
much about for about another year
but i'm working on uh i'll show you the
picture that's the poster
from the graphic novel that i'm doing
but
i'll just mention that's what i'm up to
at the moment but you you guys won't be
hearing much more about that for quite a
while because it's a long
slog getting all the artwork done and
stuff
um so yeah i think that's all i that i
had to say to to finish things up today
thanks for your questions i thought they
were really good i like and uh
i hope that you enjoyed doing the
exercise earlier as well
very cool so in a moment i will close up
with some upcoming events mcdonald
thanks so much for visiting the stoa
uh this will go on youtube so if you
want to listen to the view from above
again
you can do so um upcoming events uh
tomorrow we have one
uh daniel schmuckenberger is coming to
the stoa
um he's doing a talk on meta-modern
stoicism
so you might be interested in this one
donald to figure out what he what he
means by meta monitors and talking about
the possibilities of that
that's at 7 30 pm eastern time um
and if you'd like to support the store
you go to our patreon page
in the chat right there all right thank
you everyone
for visiting the store today